{
  "reference_number": "10262",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The target should be brought forward. The planet is in a precarious situation and we should be on a \"war\" footing to ensure that all\n measures necessary are put in place to reduce / eliminate emissions to a safe level to ensure a sustainable future."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "The most rapid cuts must occur immediately. The farming sector must be included. Methane reductions must be immediate,\n significant and not some token gesture relative to past emissions. Nitrous oxide must be included due to the rapid increase of\n\n nitrogenous fertiliser, which is also effecting our water quality."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "There must not be any creative accounting using Forest credits or overseas carbon credits. Emission reductions must be real.\n Fronterra or anyone else must not be allowed to start any new coal powered facilities and must be required to immediately phase out\n existing coal use as there are clear alternatives available. It is also bizarre that Kiwi rail is switching from electric to diesel locomotives."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Reduction targets could be brought forward if there is new scientific evidence."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only to speed up the rate of emission reductions."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There must be strict time frames of 6 months after emission budget set."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Plans must be comprehensive, environmentally sustainable, cost effective and fair. For example the current growth in tourism\nnumbers has significant effects on emissions / climate change and is not environmentally sustainable"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The changing climate and possible reduction measures could potentially effect public heath. Therefore there would be merit in a\n\nmember of the commission having expertise in these effects on public health."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Central Government desperately needs to provide leadership for local and regional government. District and Regional Plans and new\n\ninfrastructure must take into consideration the effects of climate change. These local authorities must have clear guidelines set by\ncentral government. Requires a National Climate Risk Assessment and Adaptation Programme."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government desperately needs to take leadership on this issue. The recent Ipos poll shows an overwhelming number of New\nZealanders believe in climate change and that immediate action is required. Unfortunately they also didn't think that adequate action\n\nwill be taken. Action cannot be left to individuals, companies or the market. The Government must must act."
    }
  ]
}
